Imagine you're in Rome,
تخيل أنك في روما
and you've made your way to the Vatican Museums.
و قد وصلت إلى متاحف الفاتيكان.
And you've been shuffling down long corridors,
وبدأت تتنقل عبر الممرات الطويلة،
past statues, frescoes, lots and lots of stuff.
تمر بجانب التماثيل و اللوحات الجدارية و العديد من الأشياء.
You're heading towards the Sistine Chapel.
أنت متجه نحو كنيسة سيستينا.
At last -- a long corridor, a stair and a door.
و أخيرا، ممر طويل و سلم و باب.
You're at the threshold of the Sistine Chapel.
أنت على عتبة كنيىسة سيستينا.
So what are you expecting?
فما الذي تتوقعه؟
Soaring domes? Choirs of angels?
قبب مرتفعة؟ جوقات ملائكية؟
We don't really have any of that there.
ليس لدينا أيٌ منها هناك.
Instead, you may ask yourself, what do we have?
بدلاً من ذلك، قد تسأل نفسك، ماذا لدينا؟
Well, curtains up on the Sistine Chapel.
حسناً، ارفعو الستائر عن كنيسة (سيستينا).
And I mean literally, you're surrounded by painted curtains,
وأنا أعني ذلك حرفيا فأنت محاط بستائر مرسوم عليها،
the original decoration of this chapel.
و هي الديكور الأصلي لهذه الكنيسة.
Churches used tapestries not just to keep out cold during long masses,
استعملت الكنائس القماش ليس فقط لتجنب البرد خلال القداس،
but as a way to represent the great theater of life.
بل أيضاً كطريقة لتمثيل مسرح الحياة العظيم.
The human drama in which each one of us plays a part is a great story,
إنها لقصة عظيمة، تلك الدراما الإنسانية التي يلعب كل واحد منا دورا فيها
a story that encompasses the whole world
قصة تشمل العالم أجمع
and that came to unfold in the three stages
و التي انكشفت عبر المراحل الثلاث
of the painting in the Sistine Chapel.
من الرسم في كنيسة (سيستينا).
Now, this building started out as a space for a small group
الآن، بدأ هذا البناء كحيز لمجموعة صغيرة
of wealthy, educated Christian priests.
من الكهنة المسيحيين الأغنياء المتعلمين.
They prayed there. They elected their pope there.
لقد صلوا هناك، و انتخبو الحبر الأعظم هناك.
Five hundred years ago,
قبل 500سنة
it was the ultimate ecclesiastical man cave.
كان هذا أوضح مثال عن الكهف الكنسي.
So, you may ask, how can it be that today it attracts and delights
قد تتساءل إذن كيف يمكن لها اليوم أن تجذب و تبهج
five million people a year,
5 ملايين شخص في السنة،
from all different backgrounds?
من مختلف الخلفيات؟
Because in that compressed space, there was a creative explosion,
لأنه في ذلك الحيز الصغير حدث انفجار إبداعي،
ignited by the electric excitement of new geopolitical frontiers,
كان سببه الحماس الكبير تجاه حدود الجغرافية السياسية الجديدة
which set on fire the ancient missionary tradition of the Church
و التي أحدتث ثورة في التقاليد التبشيرية للكنيسة
and produced one of the greatest works of art in history.
و أنتجت واحدة من أعظم الأعمال الفنية في التاريخ.
Now, this development took place as a great evolution,
الآن، حدث هذا التقدم على هيئة تطور عظيم،
moving from the beginning of a few elite,
بدأ من النخبة القليلة،
and eventually able to speak to audiences of people
و في النهاية كان قادراً على التواصل مع جماهير من الناس
that come from all over the world.
الآتية من كل أقطار العالم.
This evolution took place in three stages,
حدث هذا التطور خلال ثلاث مراحل،
each one linked to a historical circumstance.
كل مرحلة مرتبطة بوضع تاريخي معين.
The first one was rather limited in scope.
المرحلة الأولى كانت محدودة النطاق.
It reflected the rather parochial perspective.
و قد عكست وجهة نظر ضيقة.
The second one took place after worldviews were dramatically altered
الثانية حدثت بعدما تغيرت وجهات النظر العالمية بشكل كبير
after Columbus's historical voyage;
بعد رحلة (كولومبس) التاريخية
and the third,
و الثالثة؛
when the Age of Discovery was well under way
كانت خلال عصر الاكتشافات
and the Church rose to the challenge
و ارتقت الكنيسة لمستوى التحدي
of going global.
بأن تصبح عالمية.
The original decoration of this church reflected a smaller world.
عكس الديكور الأصلي للكنيسة عالما أصغر
There were busy scenes
كانت هناك مشاهد مزدحمة
that told the stories of the lives of Jesus and Moses,
روت قصصا عن حياة يسوع و موسى،
reflecting the development of the Jewish and Christian people.
وأظهرت تطور شعوب النصارى و اليهود
The man who commissioned this, Pope Sixtus IV,
البابا (سيكتوس الرابع)، الذي أمر برسم هذا،
assembled a dream team of Florentine art,
جمع فريقا من نخبة محترفي الفن الفلورنسي،
including men like Sandro Botticelli
من ضمنهم رجال مثل (ساندرو بوتيتشيلي)
and the man who would become Michelangelo's future painting teacher,
و الرجل الذي سيصبح أستاذ الرسم المستقبلي لـ (مايكل انجلو)،
Ghirlandaio.
(غرلندايو).
These men, they blanketed the walls with a frieze of pure color,
غطى هؤلاء الرجال الجدران بأفريز من اللون الصافي
and in these stories you'll notice familiar landscapes,
و ستلاحظ مناظر مألوفة في هذه القصص،
the artists using Roman monuments or a Tuscan landscape
فالفنانون يستعملون الآثار الرومانية أو المناظر التوسكانية
to render a faraway story, something much more familiar.
ليحولوا القصص القديمة إلى شيء مألوف أكثر
With the addition of images of the Pope's friends and family,
مع إضافة صور لعائلة و أصدقاء البابا.
this was a perfect decoration for a small court
كان هذا الديكور المثالي لبلاط صغير
limited to the European continent.
حدوده لا تتعدى القارة الأوروبية.
But in 1492, the New World was discovered,
و لكن في عام 1492، تم اكتشاف العالم الجديد
horizons were expanding,
و كانت الآفاق في توسع
and this little 133 by 46-foot microcosm had to expand as well.
فكان على هذا العالم الصغير ذي الـ 133 في 46 قدما أن يتوسع
And it did,
و هذا ما حدث بالفعل
thanks to a creative genius,
بفضل مبتكر عبقري،
a visionary and an awesome story.
ذي رؤية، و قصة رائعة.
Now, the creative genius was Michelangelo Buonarroti,
كان المبتكر العبقري (مايكيل أنجلو بيوناروتي)
33 years old when he was tapped to decorate 12,000 square feet of ceiling,
كان عمره 33 عاما عندما طلب منه تزيين سقف من 12000 متر مربع
and the deck was stacked against him --
و كانت المهمة غير عادلة بالنسبة له
he had trained in painting but had left to pursue sculpture.
كان قد تدرب على الرسم و لكن تركه لممارسة فن النحت.
There were angry patrons in Florence because he had left a stack
غضب عليه الرعاة في فلورنسا لأنه خلف وراءه كومة
of incomplete commissions,
من المهام غير المكتملة،
lured to Rome by the prospect of a great sculptural project,
وقد جذبه ازدهار مشروع عظيم للنحت إلى روما،
and that project had fallen through.
و فشل ذلك المشروع.
And he had been left with a commission to paint 12 apostles
و تم تكليفه بمهمة لرسم اثني عشرة حواريا
against a decorative background in the Sistine Chapel ceiling,
على خلفية مزينة في سقف كنيسة (سيستينا)،
which would look like every other ceiling in Italy.
و الذي كان ليبدو كجميع سقوف إيطاليا
But genius rose to the challenge.
لكن العبقري كان أهلاً للتحدي.
In an age when a man dared to sail across the Atlantic Ocean,
في عصر تجرأ فيه الإنسان على الإبحار خلال المحيط الأطلسي
Michelangelo dared to chart new artistic waters.
تجرأ (مايكل أنجلو) على خلق أساليب فنية غير مألوفة.
He, too, would tell a story --
هو أيضا كان ليروي قصة --
no Apostles -- but a story of great beginnings,
ليس قصة الحواريين، بل قصة البدايات العظيمة؛
the story of Genesis.
قصة سفر التكوين.
Not really an easy sell, stories on a ceiling.
ليس من السهل رسم قصص على السقف.
How would you be able to read a busy scene from 62 feet below?
فكيف يمكن قراءة مشهد ملحمي يعلوك بـ 62 قدما؟
The painting technique that had been handed on for 200 years
تقنية الرسم التي ثم توارثها لـ 200 عام
in Florentine studios was not equipped for this kind of a narrative.
في ورشات فلورنسا، لم تكن معدّة لهذا النوع من القصص
But Michelangelo wasn't really a painter,
لكن (مايكل أنجلو) لم يكن رساماً حقا،
and so he played to his strengths.
و لذلك استخدم نقاط قوته.
Instead of being accustomed to filling space with busyness,
بدلا من ملئ الفراغ برسومات
he took a hammer and chisel and hacked away at a piece of marble
أخذ مطرقة و منقاشا و نحت في قطعة من الرخام
to reveal the figure within.
لكي يظهر الشكل المخفي داخلها.
Michelangelo was an essentialist;
كان (مايكل أنجلو) جوهرياً،
he would tell his story in massive, dynamic bodies.
كان ليحكي قصته عبر أجسام ضخمة و حيوية.
This plan was embraced by the larger-than-life Pope Julius II,
و قد شجع البابا (يوليوس الثاني) هذه الخطة
a man who was unafraid of Michelangelo's brazen genius.
هذا الرجل الذي لم يكن خائفا من عبقرية (مايكل أنجلو) الجريئة.
He was nephew to Pope Sixtus IV,
لقد كان ابن أخ البابا (سيكتوس الرابع)،
and he had been steeped in art for 30 years and he knew its power.
و قد كان منغمسا في الفن لثلاثين عاما و أدرك قوته.
And history has handed down the moniker of the Warrior Pope,
و قد لقبه التاريخ بالـ (البابا المحارب)
but this man's legacy to the Vatican -- it wasn't fortresses and artillery,
لكن إرث هذا الرجل للفاتيكان لم يكن لا قلاعا ولا عتادا،
it was art.
بل كان فنا.
He left us the Raphael Rooms, the Sistine Chapel.
لقد ترك لنا غرف رافاييل و كنيسة سيستين.
He left St. Peter's Basilica
و كاتدرائية القديس بطرس
as well as an extraordinary collection of Greco-Roman sculptures --
بالإضافة إلى مجموعة مميزة من المنحوتات اليونانية الرومانية--
decidedly un-Christian works that would become the seedbed
هذه الأعمال غير المسيحية بلا ريب و التي ستصبح منبعاً
of the world's first modern museum, the Vatican Museums.
لأول متحف للفن الحديث. مثحف الفاتيكان.
Julius was a man
كان يوليوس رجلاً
who envisioned a Vatican that would be eternally relevant
وضع تصورا للفاتيكان حتى يبقي مواكبا للعصر للأبد
through grandeur and through beauty,
بعظمته و جماله،
and he was right.
و كان على حق.
The encounter between these two giants, Michelangelo and Julius II,
أفضى هذا المزيج بين هذين العملاقين ( مايكل أنجلو) و (يوليوس الثاني)،
that's what gave us the Sistine Chapel.
إلى ولادة كنيسة (سيستينا).
Michelangelo was so committed to this project,
كرس ( مايكل أنجلو) نفسه لهذا المشروع
that he succeeded in getting the job done in three and a half years,
لدرجة أنه انتهي منه في ثلاث سنوات و نصف،
using a skeleton crew and spending most of the time, hours on end,
بمساعدة أقل عدد من العمال و قضاء ساعات بلا انقطاع،
reaching up above his head to paint the stories on the ceiling.
ناظراً إلى الأعلى ليرسم القصص على السقف.
So let's look at this ceiling
إذن، دعونا نلقي نظرة على السقف
and see storytelling gone global.
لنرى فن رواية القصص ينتشر عالمياً.
No more familiar artistic references to the world around you.
لا مزيد من الإشارات الفنية المألوفة للعالم حولك.
There's just space and structure and energy;
ليس هناك سوى الفراغ و البنية و الطاقة،
a monumental painted framework which opens onto nine panels,
هنا تجد إطاراً فنياً هائلاً يطل على 9 لوحات أخرى،
more driven by sculptural form than painterly color.
معتمدة على التكوين النحتي أكثر من الألوان المرسومة.
And we stand in the far end by the entrance,
حين نقف في النهاية البعيدة عند المدخل،
far from the altar and from the gated enclosure intended for the clergy
بعيدا عن مذبح الكنيسة وعن السياج الخاص بالكهنة
and we peer into the distance, looking for a beginning.
و نمعن النظر في هذا الأفق باحثين عن بداية.
And whether in scientific inquiry or in biblical tradition,
و سواء في البحث العلمي أو في التقاليد الإنجيلية،
we think in terms of a primal spark.
فنحن نفكر حيث انطلقت شرارة البداية
Michelangelo gave us an initial energy
وهبنا (مايكل أنجلو) طاقة البداية
when he gave us the separation of light and dark,
عندما نحت لنا انفصال النور عن الظلام،
a churning figure blurry in the distance,
شكل مضطرب باهت في الأفق،
compressed into a tight space.
مضغوط في حيز ضيق
The next figure looms larger,
يرتسم الشكل التالي بشكل أكبر،
and you see a figure hurtling from one side to the next.
و ترى شكلا يندفع من جانب إلى الجانب الذي يليه.
He leaves in his wake the sun, the moon, vegetation.
و في يقظته، يترك لنا الشمس و القمر و النباتات.
Michelangelo didn't focus on the stuff that was being created,
لم يركز (مايكل أنجلو) على الأشياء التي تُخلق.
unlike all the other artists.
على خلاف غيره من الفنانين.
He focused on the act of creation.
و إنما ركز على عملية الخلق.
And then the movement stops, like a caesura in poetry
و عندها تتوقف الحركة، كالوقف عند منتصف البيت الشعري
and the creator hovers.
و يحلق الخالق.
So what's he doing?
إذن، ما الذي يفعله؟
Is he creating land? Is he creating sea?
هل يخلق الأرض؟ هل يخلق البحر؟
Or is he looking back over his handiwork, the universe and his treasures,
أم أنه يعيد النظر إلى خلقه و الكون و كنوزه،
just like Michelangelo must have,
تماما كما كان يفعل (مايكل أنجلو)
looking back over his work in the ceiling
حين يعيد النظر إلى عمله على السقف
and proclaiming, "It is good."
مؤكدا: "إنه جيد"
So now the scene is set,
و الآن، لقد أعد المشهد
and you get to the culmination of creation, which is man.
حتى عندما تصل لذروة الخلق، أي الإنسان.
Adam leaps to the eye, a light figure against a dark background.
يظهر آدم في المشهد، مخلوق مضيء على خلفية مظلمة.
But looking closer,
و لكن حين تمعن النظر،
that leg is pretty languid on the ground,
ترى قدمه واهنة علي الأرض،
the arm is heavy on the knee.
و ذراعه ثقيلة على ركبته.
Adam lacks that interior spark
يفتقر آدم إلى ذلك البريق الداخلي
that will impel him to greatness.
الذي سيقوده إلى العظمة.
That spark is about to be conferred by the creator in that finger,
يوشك الخالق على منح الشرارة إلى ذلك الأصبع،
which is one millimeter from the hand of Adam.
الذي يبعد مليمترا واحدا عن يد آدم.
It puts us at the edge of our seats,
مما يجعلنا نجلس على حافة مقعدنا من الترقب،
because we're one moment from that contact,
فما هي إلا لحظة و يحدث التلامس،
through which that man will discover his purpose,
الذي سيكتشف هذا الرجل من خلاله الهدف من وجوده،
leap up and take his place at the pinnacle of creation.
و يثب ليأخذ مكانه في قمة هرم الخلق.
And then Michelangelo threw a curveball.
بعد ذلك فاجأنا (مايكل أنجلو).
Who is in that other arm?
لمن هذه الذراع الأخرى؟
Eve, first woman.
إنها حواء، المرأة الأولى.
No, she's not an afterthought. She's part of the plan.
لا، إنها ليست فكرة عرضية، بل هي جزء من الخطة.
She's always been in his mind.
لقد كانت دائما في عقله.
Look at her, so intimate with God that her hand curls around his arm.
انظر إليها، حميمية جدا مع الإله حتى أنها تشبك يدها في ذراعه
And for me, an American art historian from the 21st century,
و بالنسبة إلي، كمؤرخة للفن الأمريكي من القرن الحادي عشر،
this was the moment that the painting spoke to me.
كانت هذه هي اللحظة التي تحدثت فيها اللوحة إليّ.
Because I realized that this representation of the human drama
لأنني أدركت أن هذا التمثيل للدراما الإنسانية
was always about men and women --
لطالما كان عن المرأة و الرجل--
so much so, that the dead center, the heart of the ceiling,
لدرجة أن نقطة المركز، في قلب ذاك السقف،
is the creation of woman, not Adam.
صورت خلق حواء، و ليس آدم.
And the fact is, that when you see them together in the Garden of Eden,
و الحقيقة أنه عندما تشاهدهما معا في جنة الخلد،
they fall together
ستراهما يطردان منها معا أيضا
and together their proud posture turns into folded shame.
و معا، سيتحول ل فخرهما بنفسيهما إلي عار مستتر.
You are at critical juncture now in the ceiling.
أنت الآن في نقطة مهمة في لوحة السقف.
You are exactly at the point where you and I can go
أنت تماما في نقطة لا يمكننا لا أنا و لا أنت أن نذهب
no further into the church.
أبعد منها في الكنيسة.
The gated enclosure keeps us out of the inner sanctum,
حيث يمنعنا السياج المغلق من العبور إلي الحرم الداخلي،
and we are cast out much like Adam and Eve.
مطرودين تماما كآدم و حواء
The remaining scenes in the ceiling,
المشاهد المتبقية في السقف،
they mirror the crowded chaos of the world around us.
تعكس الفوضى التي تملأ العالم من حولنا.
You have Noah and his Ark and the flood.
ها هو نوح و سفينته و الطوفان.
You have Noah. He's making a sacrifice and a covenant with God.
و ها هو نوح يقوم بتضحية و عهد مع الله.
Maybe he's the savior.
ربما يكون هو المنقذ.
Oh, but no, Noah is the one who grew grapes, invented wine,
لكن لا، لقد كان نوح هو من زرع العنب و ابتكر النبيذ،
got drunk and passed out naked in his barn.
و شرب حتى الثمالة و فقد وعيه في مخزنه.
It is a curious way to design the ceiling,
إنها لطريقة مثيرة للفضول أن تصمم السقف،
now starting out with God creating life,
يبدأ الآن بإله يخلق الحياة،
ending up with some guy blind drunk in a barn.
و ينتهي برجل ثمل داخل مخزن.
And so, compared with Adam,
و لذلك، مقارنة بآدم،
you might think Michelangelo is making fun of us.
ربما تظن أن (مايكل أنجلو) يسخر منا.
But he's about to dispel the gloom
لكنه على وشك أن يزيح الغمام
by using those bright colors right underneath Noah:
مستخدما تلك الألوان الساطعة تماما أسفل نوح:
emerald, topaz, scarlet on the prophet Zechariah.
الزمرد و حجر التوباز و صورة النبي زكريا ملونة بالقرمزي.
Zechariah foresees a light coming from the east,
يرى زكريا نورا يطل من الشرق،
and we are turned at this juncture to a new destination,
و في هذه النقطة نتحول إلي وجهة أخرى،
with sibyls and prophets who will lead us on a parade.
حيث يقود الأنبياء و العرافات موكبنا.
You have the heroes and heroines who make safe the way,
ها هم أبطال و بطلات يؤمنون الطريق،
and we follow the mothers and fathers.
و نحن نتبع الآباء و الأمهات
They are the motors of this great human engine, driving it forward.
إنهم وقود المحرك الإنساني العظيم، يدفعونه إلى الأمام.
And now we're at the keystone of the ceiling,
و الآن نحن عند حجر زاوية السقف،
the culmination of the whole thing,
ذروة الأمر برمته،
with a figure that looks like he's about to fall out of his space
بصورة يبدو فيها و كأنه على وشك السقوط من فضائه
into our space,
إلى فضائنا،
encroaching our space.
متخطيا إياه.
This is the most important juncture.
هذه هي أهم نقطة على الإطلاق.
Past meets present.
حيث يلتقي الماضي بالحاضر.
This figure, Jonah, who spent three days in the belly of the whale,
هذه صورة يونس الذي قضى ثلاثة أيام في بطن الحوت،
for the Christians, is the symbol of the renewal of humanity
و الذي يمثل للمسيحيين رمزاً في نهضة الإنسانية
through Jesus' sacrifice,
من خلال تضحية المسيح،
but for the multitudes of visitors to that museum
بينما للجموع التي تزور المتحف
from all faiths who visit there every day,
من كل الأديان التي تتوارد كل يوم،
he is the moment the distant past encounters and meets immediate reality.
فهو يمثل اللحظة التي يلتقي فيها الماضي السحيق بالواقع الحاضر.
All of this brings us to the yawning archway of the altar wall,
كل هذا يقودنا إلى الممر الشاسع لجدار المذبح،
where we see Michelangelo's Last Judgment,
حيث نرى لوحة "يوم القيامة" لـ (مايكل أنجلو)،
painted in 1534 after the world had changed again.
و التي رسمت في عام 1534 بعدما تغير العالم ثانيةً.
The Reformation had splintered the Church,
قسّمت حركة الإصلاح الكنيسة،
the Ottoman Empire had made Islam a household word
وجعلت الإمبراطورية العثمانية "الإسلام" كلمة مألوفة
and Magellan had found a route into the Pacific Ocean.
و وجد (ماجلان) طريقا إلى المحيط الهادي.
How is a 59-year-old artist who has never been any further than Venice
كيف لفنان يبلغ 59 عاما و لم يسافر أبعد من حدود فينيسيا
going to speak to this new world?
أن يتحدث إلى هذا العالم الجديد؟
Michelangelo chose to paint destiny,
اختار (مايكل أنجلو) أن يرسم القدر،
that universal desire,
تلك الرغبة العالمية،
common to all of us,
التي نشترك فيها جميعا،
to leave a legacy of excellence.
ليترك إرثاً من التميز.
Told in terms of the Christian vision of the Last Judgment,
يحكي (مايكل أنجلو) نهاية العالم في ظل الرؤية المسيحية،
the end of the world,
ليوم القيامة،
Michelangelo gave you a series of figures
أعطانا (مايكل أنجلو) سلسلة من الصور
who are wearing these strikingly beautiful bodies.
لأجساد جميلة بشكل جذّاب.
They have no more covers, no more portraits
لا يملكون مزيداً من الملابس، لا مزيد من الوجوه
except for a couple.
عدا اثنين منهم
It's a composition only out of bodies,
إنها لوحة للأجساد فقط
391, no two alike,
391 جسد، لا يشبه أي منهم الآخر،
unique like each and every one of us.
فريد من نوعه، ككل واحد منا.
They start in the lower corner, breaking away from the ground,
يبدؤون من الركن السفلي منطلقين من الأرض،
struggling and trying to rise.
يحاولون في معاناة أن يرتفعوا.
Those who have risen reach back to help others,
و من نجح منهم يعود ليساعد الآخرين،
and in one amazing vignette,
و في لقطة واحدة مدهشة،
you have a black man and a white man pulled up together
تجد رجلاً أسود و رجلاً أبيض يرتفعان معاً
in an incredible vision of human unity
في صورة مذهلة لتوحد الإنسانية
in this new world.
في هذا العالم الجديد.
The lion's share of the space goes to the winner's circle.
يذهب نصيب الأسد من الحيز إلى نخبة الفائزين.
There you find men and women completely nude like athletes.
هناك تجد الرجال و النساء عرايا تماماً كالرياضيين.
They are the ones who have overcome adversity,
لقد تجاوزوا المحنة،
and Michelangelo's vision of people who combat adversity,
و الصورة التي في ذهن (مايكل أنجلو) لأولئك الذين كافحوا المحنة،
overcome obstacles --
و تجاوزوا الصعاب--
they're just like athletes.
تشبه تماما صورة الرياضيين.
So you have men and women flexing and posing
إذن، تجد رجالا و نساءً يتموضعون برشاقة
in this extraordinary spotlight.
تحت تلك الأضواء المدهشة.
Presiding over this assembly is Jesus,
و المسيح يترأس هذا التجمع،
first a suffering man on the cross,
في البداية كرجل يعاني على الصليب،
now a glorious ruler in Heaven.
و الآن كقائد عظيم في السماء.
And as Michelangelo proved in his painting,
و كما أثبت (مايكل أنجلو) في لوحته،
hardship, setbacks and obstacles,
الصعوبات و العوائق و العقبات،
they don't limit excellence, they forge it.
لا تقيد التميز بل تصقله.
Now, this does lead us to one odd thing.
الآن، هذا يقودنا إلى شيء غريب.
This is the Pope's private chapel,
هذه هي كنيسة البابا الخاصة،
and the best way you can describe that is indeed a stew of nudes.
و أفضل طريقة لوصفها هي "خنة من العراة".
But Michelangelo was trying to use only the best artistic language,
لكن (مايكل أنجلو) كان يحاول فقط أن يستخدم أفضل لغة فنية،
the most universal artistic language he could think of:
أفضل لغة فنية عالمية فكر بها:
that of the human body.
وهي الجسد الإنساني.
And so instead of the way of showing virtue such as fortitude or self-mastery,
و لذلك بدلا من إظهار الفضيلة على هيئة الثبات أو السيادة الذاتية،
he borrowed from Julius II's wonderful collection of sculptures
فقد استعان بمنحوتات (يوليويس الثاني) الرائعة
in order to show inner strength as external power.
لكي يظهر القوة الداخلية كمصدر للطاقة الخارجية.
Now, one contemporary did write
الآن، كتب أحد المعاصرين
that the chapel was too beautiful to not cause controversy.
أن الكنيسة كانت جميلة لدرجة أنها لابد وأن تسبب جدلا.
And so it did.
و هذا ما كان.
Michelangelo soon found that thanks to the printing press,
فبفضل الصحافة المطبوعة، وجد (مايكل أنجلو)،
complaints about the nudity spread all over the place,
شكاوي بسبب العري المنتشر في المكان،
and soon his masterpiece of human drama was labeled pornography,
و لم يلبث أن تم تصنيف تحفته عن الدراما الإنسانية على أنها إباحية،
at which point he added two more portraits,
و حينها أضاف وجهين آخرين،
one of the man who criticized him, a papal courtier,
وجه للأسقف الذي انتقده،
and the other one of himself as a dried up husk, no athlete,
و الآخر لنفسه في صورة متقشرة جافة، و ليس كرياضي،
in the hands of a long-suffering martyr.
في يد شهيد عانى طويلاً.
The year he died he saw several of these figures covered over,
في السنة التي توفي فيها شاهد العديد من هذه الصور مغطّاة،
a triumph for trivial distractions over his great exhortation to glory.
مما مثّل انتصاراً للتفاهة على سعيه إلى المجد.
And so now we stand
إذن، نحن الآن نقف
in the here and now.
هنا و الآن.
We are caught in that space
عالقين في هذا الفضاء
between beginnings and endings,
بين البدايات و النهايات،
in the great, huge totality of the human experience.
في التجربة الإنسانية الكلية و العظيمة.
The Sistine Chapel forces us to look around as if it were a mirror.
تجبرنا كنيسة (سيستينا) على النظر من حولنا كما لو كانت مرآة.
Who am I in this picture?
من أنا في هذه الصورة؟
Am I one of the crowd?
هل أنا جزء من هذا الحشد؟
Am I the drunk guy?
هل أنا الرجل الثمل؟
Am I the athlete?
هل أنا الرياضي؟
And as we leave this haven of uplifting beauty,
و بينما نغادر هذا المرفأ من الجمال الرفيع،
we are inspired to ask ourselves life's biggest questions:
يلهمنا أن نسأل أنفسنا أهم أسئلة الحياة:
Who am I, and what role do I play in this great theater of life?
من أنا؟ و ما الدور الذي ألعبه في مسرح الحياة العظيم؟
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Elizabeth Lev, thank you.
(برونو جيوساني): (إليزابيث ليف)، شكرا لكِ.
Elizabeth, you mentioned this whole issue of pornography,
(إليزابيث)، لقد ذكرت مشكلة الإباحية تلك
too many nudes and too many daily life scenes and improper things
كثير من الأجساد العارية و مشاهد من الحياة اليومية و أشياء غير لائقة
in the eyes of the time.
من وجهة نظر ذاك الزمان.
But actually the story is bigger.
و لكن في الحقيقة، القصة أكبر من ذلك.
It's not just touching up and covering up some of the figures.
ليس الأمر في تغطية بعض الصور و التعديل عليها
This work of art was almost destroyed because of that.
كاد أن يدمر هذا العمل الفني بسبب ذلك.
Elizabeth Lev: The effect of the Last Judgment was enormous.
(إليزابيث ليف): كان تأثير لوحة "يوم القيامة" كبيراً.
The printing press made sure that everybody saw it.
الصحافة المطبوعة حرصت على أن يراها الكل.
And so, this wasn't something that happened within a couple of weeks.
و لذلك، لم يحدث الأمر في أسابيع.
It was something that happened over the space of 20 years
بل على مر 20 عاماً
of editorials and complaints,
من المقالات و الشكاوى،
saying to the Church,
قائلين للكنيسة،
"You can't possibly tell us how to live our lives.
"لا يمكنك إخبارنا كيف نعيش حيواتنا.
Did you notice you have pornography in the Pope's chapel?"
هل لاحظت أن هناك صوراً إباحية في كنيسة البابا"
And so after complaints and insistence
و لذا، بعد الشكاوى و الإلحاح
of trying to get this work destroyed,
لتدمير هذا العمل،
it was finally the year that Michelangelo died
جاء العام الذي مات فيه (مايكل أنجلو)
that the Church finally found a compromise,
و نجحت الكنيسة أخيرا بإيجاد
a way to save the painting,
طريقة لتنقذ اللوحة
and that was in putting up these extra 30 covers,
بأن تضع تلك الأغطية الثلاثين الإضافية
and that happens to be the origin of fig-leafing.
و كان هذا الأصل في استعمال أوراق التين.
That's where it all came about,
كان هذا أصل كل شيء،
and it came about from a church that was trying to save a work of art,
و قد جاء من كنيسة كانت تحاول إنقاذ عمل فني،
not indeed deface or destroyed it.
و ليس لتشويهها و تدميرها.
BG: This, what you just gave us, is not the classic tour
ب.ج: هذا، ما قدمته لنا للتو، ليس جولة تقليدية
that people get today when they go to the Sistine Chapel.
يجولها الناس اليوم حين يذهبون إلى كنيسة (سيستينا)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
EL: I don't know, is that an ad?
إ.ل: لا أعلم، أهذا إعلان؟
BG: No, no, no, not necessarily, it is a statement.
(برونو جيوساني): لا لا لا، ليس بالضرورة، إنه مجرد تعليق.
The experience of art today is encountering problems.
تجارب الفن في أيامنا هذه تواجه صعوبات
Too many people want to see this there,
يرغب الكثير من الناس أن يشاهدوا هذا هناك
and the result is five million people going through that tiny door
و النتيجة هي 5 ملايين يمرون عبر هذا الباب الصغير
and experiencing it in a completely different way
و يعيشونه بطريقة مختلفة تماماً
than we just did.
عما رأيناه الآن.
EL: Right. I agree. I think it's really nice to be able to pause and look.
(إليزابيث ليف): أوافقك الرأي. أظن أنه من اللطيف أن تقف و تلقي نظرة.
But also realize, even when you're in those days,
و لكن أعلم أيضاً، حتى في تلك الأيام،
with 28,000 people a day,
و 28000 شخص يزورونه كل يوم،
even those days when you're in there with all those other people,
حتى في تلك الأيام، مع كل هؤلاء الناس،
look around you and think how amazing it is
انظر حولك و تأمل كم الأمر رائع
that some painted plaster from 500 years ago
أن بعض المنحوثات المرسومة منذ 500 عام
can still draw all those people standing side by side with you,
لا زالت تستطيع أن تجذب كل هؤلاء الواقفين بجوارك،
looking upwards with their jaws dropped.
ناظرين للأعلى و فكهم للأسفل.
It's a great statement about how beauty truly can speak to us all
إنه أجل مثال عن كيف يمكن للجمال أن يتحدث لنا جميعا
through time and through geographic space.
عبر المكان و الزمان
BG: Liz, grazie.
ب.ج: (ليز)، شكرا لكِ.
EL: Grazie a te.
إ.ل: شكرا لك
BG: Thank you.
ب.ج: شكرا لكِ
(Applause)
(تصفيق)